Guide to the records of the Musical Acoustics Research Library (MARL) M1711
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 2. John W. Coltman Collection, 1937-1994; 5.004 Linear Feet
  Dr. John W. Coltman, physicist and retired research executive of the Westinghouse Electric Corporation, has devoted much of his spare time to the study of the flute in its musical, historical and acoustical aspects. His research in musical acoustics has contributed significantly to what is known today about the behavior of the flute and organ pipes. In his professional career Dr. Coltman has received many honors for his invention and development of the x-ray image amplifier, now universally used in medical fluoroscopy. He is a member of the National Academy of Engineering, holds 22 patents and has published some 70 technical papers.
  Coltman took up the study of the flute in early school years, playing in college and graduate school, and has continued as an active participant in amateur musical activities. While a student at Case his acquaintance with Prof. Dayton C. Miller sparked an interest in the acoustical and historical aspects of the instrument, and in the 1950's he began a collection of instruments of the flute family which now numbers about 200. A little later he started inquiries into the mechanisms of sound production of these instruments, establishing a small laboratory in his home to pursue this work as a hobby. Several of his papers on this subject have contributed significantly to what is known today about the acoustics of the flute and organ pipe. In addition to the above mentioned recognition, Coltman received the Order of Merit from Westinghouse, was elected a Fellow of the American Physical Society, a Fellow of the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers, and a member of the National Academy of Engineering. He has served on many committees of the U. S. Government and was a member of the Commission on Human Resources of the National Research Council. He is the author of some 70 technical publications and hold 22 patents.
  Coltman married Charlotte Beard of Urbana, Illinois in 1941. They have two married daughters and four grandchildren. Among other pursuits are sailing, woodworking and amateur radio, for which he has been licensed since 1932.
  Coltman, John Wesley
  - Technical Papers, 1937-2006; hx229xs1245 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    Papers by John W. Coltman on Musical Acoustics
    1.01 Vibration of stretched wires (with R.S. Shankland) [135 KB, DjVu], Journal of the Franklin Institute, (September 1937). Reprinted in Musical Acoustics: Piano and Wind Instruments, edited by Earle L.Kent. Dowden, Hutchinson, and Ross (1977). 1.02 Resonance and sounding frequencies of the flute, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 40(1):99-107 (July 1966). 1.03 Sounding mechanism of the flute and organ pipe, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 44(4):983-992 (October 1968). Reprinted in Musical Acoustics: Piano and Wind Instruments, edited by Earle L.Kent. Dowden, Hutchinson, and Ross (1977). 1.04 Acoustics of the flute, Physics Today, 21(11):25-32 (November 1968). Reprinted in Physics of Music (1988). Included in Physics Teachers CD-ROM Toolkit (1993). 1.05 Sound radiation from the mouth of an organ pipe, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 46(2, part 2):477 (August 1969). 1.06 Effect of material on flute tone quality [521 KB, PDF], Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 49(2, part 2):520-523 (1971). 1.07 Acoustics of the flute, parts I and II, The Instrumentalist, Vol. XXIV, No. 6 and 7 (January and February 1972). 1.08 Material used in flute construction [275 KB, PDF], Woodwind World, 12(1):20-21 (February 1973). 1.09 Mouth resonance effects in the flute, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 54:417 (1973). Reprinted in Musical Acoustics: Piano and Wind Instruments, edited by Earle L.Kent. Dowden, Hutchinson, and Ross (1977). 1.10 The intonation of antique and modern flutes, Parts 1-4, The Instrumentalist, Vol. XXIX, No. 5, (1974-1975).
    1.11 Fifty flutists play one flute, Woodwind World, (March 1976). 1.12 Flute scales, pitch and intonation, The Instrumentalist, (May 1976). 1.13 Jet drive mechanisms in edge tones and organ pipes, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 60(3) (September 1976). 1.14 A new C# for the Boehm flute, The Instrumentalist, (May 1977). 1.15 Tuning wind instruments, Booklet produced for distribution in schools by C.G. Conn, Ltd, Oak Brook, Illinois. Revised and enlarged by John W. Coltman, 1977, 12 pp. 1.16 Acoustical analysis of the Boehm flute, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 65(2):499-506 (1979). 1.17 Book Review, Musical Acoustics: Piano and Wind Instruments (edited by Earle L.Kent), Journal of the American Musical Instrument Society, V-VI:200 (1979-1980). 1.18 Momentum transfer in jet excitation of flute-like instruments, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 69(4):1164-1168 (1981). 1.19 Book Review, The Practical Acoustics of Early Woodwinds (Herbert Myers) and La Flute Traversier a Une Clef (M. Castellengo et al), Journal of the American Musical Instrument Society, VIII:105 (1982). 1.20 Theobald Boehm and the scale of the modern flute, Journal of the American Musical Society, IX:89-111 (1983).
    1.21 Enhanced sound power from a recurved flute, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 75(5):1642-1643 (May 1984). 1.22 Observations on the high E, The Flutist Quarterly, National Flute Association, Vol. X, No. 2 (Winter 1984). 1.23 Some flute myths as seen by a scientist, The Flute Forum, Elkhart, Indiana (Summer 1985). 1.24 Role of the headjoint in flute intonation [79 KB, DjVu], Flute Notes, London, (1985). 1.25 Book Review, Elements D'Acoustique Musicale et Instrumental (Victor Charles Mahillon) [117 KB, DjVu], Journal of the American Musical Instrument Society, XI:179-182 (1985). 1.26 Questions and answers on flute acoustics, The Flutist Quarterly, National Flute Association. 1.26a XIV(2):72 (Spring 1989). 1.26b XIV(5):63 (Winter 1989). 1.26c XV(3):48 (Summer 1990). 1.27 Mode stretching and harmonic generation in the flute, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 88(5) (November 1990). 1.28 Some observations on the piccolo, The Flutist Quarterly, National Flute Association, Vol. XV, No. 5 (Winter 1990). 1.29 Time domain simulation of the flute, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 92(1):69-73 (July 1992). 1.30 Jet behavior in the flute, Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 92(1):74-83 (1992).
    1.31 Headjoint acoustics - A comparison, The Woodwind Quarterly, Issue 1, pp. 8-13 (May 1993). 1.32 Acoustical losses in the Boehm flute, The Flutist Quarterly, National Flute Association, XIX(1):37-41 (Fall 1993). 1.33 Charles "Teach'em" Howe and the Howe model flute, Newsletter of the American Musical Instrument Society, Vol.XXII, No. 3 (October 1993). 1.34 Book Review, Tuning: Containing the Perfection of 18th Century Temperament... (Owen H. Jorgensen). Journal of the American Musical Instrument Society, Vol. XIX, pp. 105-109 (1993). 1.35 Designing the scale of the Boehm flute [2.1 MB, PDF], The Woodwind Quarterly, Issue 4, pp. 24-41 (February 1994). 1.36 Acoustical losses of bassoon pads (with James Parker), The Double Reed (Journal of the International Double Reed Society), pp. 43-45 (Winter 1994). 1.37 Just noticeable differences in timbre of the flute, Catgut Acoustical Society Journal, Vol. 3, No. 1 (Series II) (May 1996). 1.38 The influence of mode spacing on the sound of early flutes, The Woodwind Quarterly, Issue 13 (Fall 1996). 1.39 Properties of woodwind instrument bores, The Woodwind Quarterly, Issue 14, 1997. 1.40 Flute intonation in performance, The Flutist Quarterly, Vol. XXIV, No. 1 (Fall 1998).
    1.41 Acoustical losses in flute pads [3.4 MB, PDF] The Journal of Musical Instrument Technology, Issue 23 (Spring 2003). 1.42 Acoustical losses in wet instrument bores. Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 114(3) September 2003. 1.43 Jet offset, harmonic content, and warble in the flute. Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 120(4):2312-2319, October 2006. 1.44 Acoustic properties of miter bends. [188 KB, PDF] Unpublished, December 2006. 1.45 Compensating for miter bends in cylindrical tubing. [45 KB, PDF] Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 121(3):2497-2498, May 2007.
  - Reports and Memoranda, 1974-1997; rn369ry4119 (Box 61, Folder 2)
    Intonation of the Murray Flute; Letter to Alex Murray - Tests of Flute in F; Characterizing Finger holes in the Modern Flute; Report on Armstrong Prototype Flutes; Letter to Al Singleton; Acoustic Parameters of Flute Holes and Keys 4pp + Figs; Report on Cooper-Scale Powell Flute, 3pp +Figures; Letter to Bickford Brannen 12/8/75; Letter from Mark Thomas, Armstrong, 4/8/76; Letter to Jack Moore with measurements of Cooper Scale Flute; Bibliography on Flute Acoustics - Letter to Carleton Sperati; Intonation Changes due to the C# vent; Resonances of Three Alto Saxophones (Report to C. G. Conn, Ltd; Letter to Gary Sigurdson, (Conn) with further info on Three Alto Saxes; Resonances of Four Alto Saxophones - Report to Conn; Letter to Gary Sigurdson (Conn) with discussion of 2.09, 2.10 and 2.11; Report on Murray Flute in F (Jack Moore and A. K. Cooper), 4pp; Report on Murray Piccolo; Intonation Comparisons of Alto Saxophones (for C. G. Conn Ltd.; Neck Bore Modifications for an E-flat Alto Sax, report to C. G. Conn, Ltd.; Patent disclosure: Tuning adjustment for saxophones or reed instruments; Report on Murray - Moore gold flute #42; Leak measurement in the Boehm flute; A flute with square holes - Leonard Lopatin; Wind instruments and tone quality - panel presentation.
  - Referee's Remarks on Papers Reviewed for Publication, 1973-1998; bz079ns8564 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    Elder, S. A.On the mechanism of sound production in organ pipes; Fletcher, N. H Non-linear interactions in organ pipes; Nederveen, C. J Frequencies of the flute; Fletcher, N. H. Acoustic correlates of flute performance techniques; Fletcher, N. H.Jet drive mechanism in organ pipes; Fletcher, N. H.Sound production by organ flue pipes; Rauch, H. E.Jet driven musical instruments and the edge tone; Fletcher, N. H. Sound production by organ flue pipes - 2nd edition; Backus, John. The Acoustical Foundations of Music; Elder, S. S. On the edge tone contribution to pipe-coupled resonators; Fletcher, N. H. Wave propagation on an Air Jet; Elder, S. A. Edgetones vs. Pipetones; Hall, Don. Musical Acoustics, Chapter 11; Nolle A. W.Some voicing adjustments of flue organ pipes; Lyng and Lee. A differential-difference equation occurring in edge tone theory; Phelan, James. The complete guide to the flute; Keefe, D. H.Acoustical streaming and tone hole interaction; Nolle, A. W. Adjustments affecting the steady waveform of flue organ pipes; Thwaites, S. The turbulent jet in organ flue pipes; Keefe, D. H.Woodwind air column models; Elder S. A.On the theory of resonant cavity excitation by an unstable source; Valeriu, I.Time domain simulation and linear analysis of organ pipes; Verge, M. P. Jet formation and jet velocity fluctuations in a flue organ pipe; Fagan, E. Whistles; Verge, M. P. Jet oscillations and jet drive in recorder-like instruments; Wilson et al. Input response of cylindrical and conical bores; Fletcher, N. H. Paper on flute; Fabre, B. et al. Vortex shedding; Adachi et al. Time domain simulations of sound production in an organ pipe; Yoshikawa, S. A pictorial insight into organ pipe physics; Verge et al. Sound production in flute-like instruments; Nolle, A.W.Sinuous instability of a planar air jet; Yoshikawa, S. Jet wave amplification in organ pipes; Hopkin, Bart. Musical instrument design.
  - Correspondence, 1952-1972; mm055gc2507 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1979; xt544rq8510 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1985; qx596nt1726 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1989; nk262rw0745 (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1993; mj053rv6604 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1998; hb021kx4331 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Acoustic properties of pipes; Played frequencies of flute specimens; Resonance and sounding frequencies; Acoustic properties of pipes, 1959-1965; xg765fx4058 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Impedance of jet, strobe photos of jet, 1967-1968; tt588zq1868 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Phase velocity on jet, Q of pipes, characterizing instruments; Experiment on double organ pipe; Experiment on mouth resonance effects; Test flutes of different materials, side holes, artificial blowing., 1968-1970; pf905vd5706 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Technical Notes: Jet drive mechanisms in edge tones; Finger holes in the Boehm flute; Drive mechanisms in organ pipes, 1970; km067hd8787 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Technical Notes: Acoustically excited free jet; Further calculations on organ pipe drives; The Intonation of Antique and Modern Flutes., 1972; kr647xr5813; Notes from 2/11/72 to 3/9/73 are missing (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Resonances, blowing effects, intonation; Finger holes, keys and cavities, 1973-1974; tb195cm3694 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Murray Flute - Armstrong prototype; Non-Linear effects in closed tubes; Fifty Flutists -- Tests of flute at NFA Convention; Cooper Scale flutes, 1974-1976; ry583hm8658 (Box 64, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: No cavity flute, Cooper-Powell, misc. calculations; Jack Moore and his flutes; Analyses of lossy flute using Smith chart impedance diagram; A new C# for the Boehm Flute, 1975-1976; kc345fk3952 (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Alto Saxophone Measurements; Tee head, flute designs, cork considerations, 1976-1977; 5.27-5.28 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Wavelength, multiphonics, flute in F and piccolo, porosity in wall, 1978; 5.29 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Scales of various flutes, High E modes, jet wave analysis; Intonation studies of Alto Saxophones for Conn Artley Division, 1979; 5.30-5.31 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Momentum transfer in jet excitation of flute-like instruments; Correspondence with William Strong, 1979-1980; 5.32-5.33 (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: The trumpet as a parametric oscillator; Conical bores, Powell dimensions, blown resonator, E5 tone, 1981; 5.34-5.35 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Bore size, mode inharmonicity, recurved head, some flutes; Theobald Boehm and the scale of the modern flute, Part 1, 1981; 5.36-5.37 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Theobald Boehm and the scale of the modern flute, Part 2., 1982-1983; 5.38 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Recurved heads, Emerson, Moore, & Wimberly flutes, tone holes; Coltman scale, Wimberly, 1983-1984; 5.39-5.40 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Alto flutes; Coltman design of alto flute for Emerson, 1983-1995; 5.41 - 5.42 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Recorder stability, Shakuhachi head, trill key positions; Drelinger headjoint, jet excursions, Tom Green flute, 1984-1985; 5.43-5.44 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Smooth bore flute, split E, stepped head joint, Wimberly #42; Time domain simulation of the flute, Part 1, 1983-1986; 5.45-5.46 (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Time domain simulation of the flute, Part 2, 1984-1991; 5.47 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Behavior of acoustically excited jet, Part 1, 1987-1989; 5.48 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Behavior of acoustically excited jet, Part 2, 1989-1991; 5.49 (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Behavior of acoustically excited jet, Part 3, 1989-1991; 5.50 (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Behavior of acoustically excited jet, Part 4; Q & A on Flute acoustics, 1990-1991; 5.51-5.52 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Bass and Contra-bass flute, 1983-1996; 5.53 (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Leak, inverted cone, BASIC programs, mode stretch, spectra, 1987-1991; 5.54 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Piccolo studies, Armstrong, Conn, several others, 1989-1996; 5.55 (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Piccolo bench measurements, 1990; 5.56 (Box 69, Folder 5)
  - Technical Notes: Hirschberg correspondence on jets, organ pipes; Tube resonances, losses in the Boehm flute, 1990-1993; pk145bz9451 (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Conical and cylindrical piccolo spectra (Rhian Kenny); Repeated impulse (spark) impedance method, 1991-1992; jb343gx7986 (Box 70, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Spectra of Goosman, Powell headjoints, Emerson flutes; Scale design of Boehm flute, Charles Teach'em Howe, 1992-1993; yr773kt3978 (Box 70, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Just noticeable differences in the timbre of the flute; Diameter, phase, oboe reed, 1994-1997; sb825np7757 (Box 70, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Mode spacing and the sound of early flutes; Losses in Bassoon pads, instrument bores, 1995-1997; 5.65-5.66 (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Head joint designs, 1995-1999; 5.67 (Box 71, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Wolfe and Smith - Acoustic impedance spectroscopy, 1996-1997; 5.68 (Box 71, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Flute intonation in performance, 1997-1998; 5.69 (Box 71, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Phelan, Hirshberg, Landell, 1993-1999; 5.70 (Box 72, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Double Helmholz experiment, flow, Ocarina aperture losses, 1999-2001; 5.71 (Box 72, Folder 2)
  - Technical Notes: Loss in apertures, transmission lines, stepped bores, pad losses, 2001-2002; 5.72; Folder contains one 3.5" computer disc (Box 72, Folder 3)
  - Technical Notes: Loss in apertures, bamboo resonator, acoustics, humidity loss, 2002-2003; 5.73 (Box 72, Folder 4)
  - Technical Notes: Toroid height, ocarinas, NY flutes, marimba resonators, C hole, miter bend, shakuhachi head, quena, keratoscope, Newgrange cave, 2003-2006; 5.74 (Box 72, Folder 5)
  - Technical Notes: Piccolo design, 2003-2004; 5.75 (Box 73, Folder 1)
  - Technical Notes: Offset Jet, 2006; 5.76 (Box 73, Folder 2)
  - Coltman's Planning Records: Donating his Papers to Stanford University, 1998-2006 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    Folder includes three 3 3/4" x 3 1/2" floppy discs. Two discs contain MARL web pages from 2006, and one Coltman's Series 6.
  - Computer Programs, 6.01-6.22; Folder contains one 3.5" computer disc (Box 73, Folder 4)
    These programs will run in Microsoft QBASIC or QUICKBASIC. Each will run as written, but to test a particular instrument or situation it is usually necessary to substitute new data in some program lines. Remarks within the program usually point out where and what to do. A minimal experience in editing QBASIC programs is required.
    6.01 FLUTEKEY.EXE Stand-alone program derives acoustic parameters of holes and keys for the Boehm flute and calculates effects of changes on intonation. See 1.35 and 6.02.
    6.02 INSTRUCT.TXT Instructions for using 6.01, FLUTEKEY.EXE.
    6.03 FLUTRES2.BAS Calculates the expected sounding frequencies for the Boehm flute in C, given the hole and key parameters. Prints an automatic plot for the entire scale, including trills, or will accept manual queries for a single note. See 1.35 and 6.04
    6.04 FLUTRESO.TXT Instructions for using 6.03, FLUTRES2.BAS.
    6.05 EXPLRESO.TXT Outlines the way the program 6.03, FLUTRES2.BAS operates.
    6.06 ALTRESO.BAS Same as 6.03 except for Alto flute in G.
    6.07 BASSRESO.BAS Same as 6.03 except for Alto flute in G.
    6.08 PICCRESO.BAS Same as 6.03 except for Cylinder piccolo in C.
    6.09 HEADCONE.BAS Calculates and plots the effective length of a C flute head joint as a function of frequency, using successive conical sections as an approximation to the taper. Routines for recurved heads and conical cork cavities included. Mouth height constant. Ref. 1.24 and 1.35.
    6.10 STRATHD2.BAS Same as 6.09 except the mouth height varies with frequency to account for lip coverage changes.
    6.11 ALTOCONE.BAS Same as 6.09 except for alto flute in G.
    6.12 BASSCONE.BAS Same as 6.09 except for bass flute.
    6.13 CONEPICC.BAS Calculates resonance frequencies for conical piccolo in C. Manual entry of fingering on line 90. Bore diameters entered in lines 510-630.
    6.14 PRESDIST.BAS Calculates and plots the pressure, stored energy, and power flow along the tube of a Boehm flute in C for any fingering. Can choose assumed frequency.
    6.15 PRESCONN.BAS Same as 6.14 except for cylindrical piccolo in C.
    6.16 MULTPHON.BAS Plots the response of a Boehm flute to injected current at the mouth hole over the entire frequency range for any fingering. The resulting peaks show frequencies that may be sounded. Particularly useful for identifying multiphonics using unorthodox fingerings.
    6.17 PHASERES.BAS Similar to 6.16 MULTPHON.BAS except that the phase is also plotted so that resonances that do not meet the feedback condition for sounding may be identified.
    6.18 MULTPICC.BAS Same as 6.16 MULTPHON.BAS except for cylindrical piccolo.
    6.19 OBOEPRE2.BAS Calculates and plots effective length of oboe air column, to examine the effects of variations in bore diameter. No finger holes.
    6.20 BASSOON.BAS Calculates and plots the pressure distribution and loss distribution over the length of a conical tube having dimensions similar to a bassoon. No finger holes.
    6.21 CURWAVL.BAS Time domain simulation of flute excited by jet. See paper 1.29 for description and 6.22 for operation.
    6.22 EXPLWAVE.TXT Explains the operation of 6.21, CURWAVL.BAS, time domain simulation.
  - Index to Coltman's work (Box 73, Folder 5)
- Series 3. Arthur H. Benade Collection, 1956-1987; 19.182 Linear Feet; Between 1982 and late 1987: After cancer was diagnosed in the fall of 1982, Benade made increased use of detailed projections (with many pages hand-drawn) for many of his lectures. Though casual in appearance, these were planned as condensed versions of his presentations, which could substitute for a more formal write-up. For his final ten months Benade was bedridden, but he used his dwindling supply of energy carefully, supervising the work of two graduate students, working out a CAD/CAM program for Carleen Hutchins, and dictating three journal articles and several shorter pieces to his wife, Virginia Benade. The journal articles appeared in 1988 in J. Acoust. Soc. Am., with the other dictated material appearing in the 1990s. The Dover reprints of his two books contain corrections made by Benade to his desk copies, accumulated over many years of teaching out of them.
  Physicist Arthur H. Benade (1925-87) earned his B.A. and Ph.D. degrees at Washington University in St. Louis. He was a professor at Case Institute of Technology/Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio, from 1952 to 1987, except for sabbatical time spent at the University of Michigan and the Indian Institute of Technology at Kanpur. His doctoral work was in cosmic rays. For his first fifteen years at Case, his declared research area was nuclear physics and instrumentation.
  When he was a teenager in India, he became curious about the workings of the two instruments he had begun to play: his grandfather's piccolo and a six-key flute bought for him in the bazaar by the family's cook. Earlier than this, his physicist father had introduced him to the work of D. C. Miller, Lord Rayleigh, and Helmholtz. This background helps explain the maturity already evident in Benade's first published writings on acoustics, which appeared in 1959 and 1960, more than twenty years after the first experimentation. Benade's fascination with musical acoustics began long before his formal studies of physics and never lagged, though for many years acoustical research was forced to be a leisure-time activity. Cancer cut short (at age 62) his hope to continue this work into old age.